<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://sanjana679.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://sanjana679.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-07-24T07:19:56+00:00</updated><id>https://sanjana679.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">In Defense of Communication Technology</title><link href="https://sanjana679.github.io/blog/2021/in-defense-of-communication-technology/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="In Defense of Communication Technology"/><published>2021-05-14T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-05-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://sanjana679.github.io/blog/2021/in-defense-of-communication-technology</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://sanjana679.github.io/blog/2021/in-defense-of-communication-technology/"><![CDATA[<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>          Agree &amp; Join LinkedIn
        
  By clicking Continue to join or sign in, you agree to LinkedIn’s User Agreement, Privacy Policy, and Cookie Policy.

                Create your free account or sign in to continue your search
              
          or
        
  By clicking Continue to join or sign in, you agree to LinkedIn’s User Agreement, Privacy Policy, and Cookie Policy.

            New to LinkedIn? Join now
          
                      or
                    
                New to LinkedIn? Join now
              
  By clicking Continue to join or sign in, you agree to LinkedIn’s User Agreement, Privacy Policy, and Cookie Policy.

      Due to the COVID-19 pandemic, everything from business meetings to college classes has moved to a digital format. With the rapid increase in the use of Zoom and other forms of digital communication, the effect of communication technology on human relationships has been questioned.
    
      My two cents about this issue - communication technology isn't inherently good or bad. It is a tool that opens the door to more human connection. This time, I will take a literary approach to proving my claim, referencing two early sci-fi books and some peer-reviewed articles. The deficiencies associated with communication technology are already well-spoken. It is common knowledge that digital communication doesn't come close to capturing the intricacies associated with human interactions. As McCormack states in his paper Dispatches from the Cage: Henry James and Information Technology, digital messages ...[have] lost...[their] connection with both its speaker and its audience and, dispatched, floats somewhere in an interpretative void (93).
    
      Link - Dispatches from the Cage: Henry James and Information Technology by Jerusha McCormack
    
      Many issues we face with communication technology were predicted well in the past - almost as long ago as the late 1800s - by authors such as E.M. Forster. In her paper, Zimmermann states, [s]uch communication mediated by machines, fear of human contact, emotional engagement, bodily weakness, frontiers of time and space blurred by virtual interactions are elements in Forsters' novel that also figure in our current scientific debates (39).
    
      Link - E.M. Forsters The Machine Stops: humans, technology, and dialogue by A.C. Zimmermann
    
      The Machine Stops by E.M. Forster tells the story of Vashti and Kuno in a world where most of the human population lives underground under the protection of the omnipotent Machine. All their desires and needs are taken care of by the Machine. People spend their lives in their rooms, communicating through video screens. Humans no longer use technology to seek what they desire, as the Machine brings everything to them. Content with their sedentary life, humans developed an aversion to the surface and direct experiences not monitored by the Machine. The only exception is Kuno, who escapes, experiencing a brief moment on the surface before being dragged back down by the Machine.
    
      Kuno tries to warn his mother, Vashti, of the impending destruction of the Machine, but she is only confused. Slowly, the Machine stops operating. Gradually, the Machine can no longer sustain human life. At this moment, humanity suddenly has its first real experience - its destruction. From the story's events, we can see that Forster intended to warn of technology's dangers and advocate direct experience.
    
      However, somewhat contradictory to Forsters' claims, face-to-face interaction between the protagonist of In the Cage and Captain Everard is where their relationship breaks apart. In the Cage by Henry James describes an unnamed London telegraphist who deciphers clues to her clients' personal lives from their telegrams from her cage at the post office. Eventually, she becomes interested in and deceived by two lovers - Captain Everard and Lady Bradeen.
    
      The telegraph is what provides the protagonist with entertainment in her mundane life. The protagonist initially draws pleasure from the various pieces of information from Captain Everard’s messages without intending to pursue a further relationship. As Cormack states to the protagonist, “[t]he cage of class remains absolute, after all - but only outside the network established by the telegraph office. Within that cage, she portends the power of the new democracy of the electronic age, in which all are levelled by the open intimacy of this revolutionary mode of communication” (91). 
    
      But upon learning of Captain Everard's wealth, she pursues him, indulging in the fantasy that she could marry him and elevate her societal status. Throughout the story, the telegraph serves to give the protagonist pieces of information about the situation between Captain Everard and Lady Bradeen. Still, it never forces her into an interpretation of the information she gets. In contrast, her face-to-face meetings with Captain Everard push the protagonist towards her incorrect assumptions about the relationship between Captain Everard and herself. Throughout the story, the protagonist remains oblivious to Captain Everard’s true intentions in talking with her and his background. The deception is only revealed after the protagonist’s conversation with Mrs. Jordan about Captain Everard’s union with Lady Bradeen and his debt. The protagonist doesn’t realize the true nature of the situation in which she has tangled herself. Whether through interacting with them through their telegrams or speaking to both Captain Everard and Lady Bradeen in person, the protagonist fails to form any kind of substantial relationship with either Captain Everard or Lady Bradeen.
    
      In contrast, Vashti and Kuno in The Machine Stops have a better understanding of one another despite not speaking face to face often or even speaking often - even despite Vashti acknowledging that “the Machine did not transmit nuances of expression. It only gave a general idea of people — an idea that was good enough for all practical purposes…”(89). Whatever the Machine can convey in its limited capacity is enough for Vashti to grasp the meaning behind her son’s words throughout their conversations at various points in the book. When the Machine stops and humankind is dying, Vashti reconciles with her son, both of them crying and hoping that humanity won’t be foolish enough to start the Machine again in the future. Both Vashti and Kuno may not have spoken much throughout their lives (and mostly spoke through the Machine), but they understand one another. They held different views from one another, but they could communicate their thoughts clearly, even over an indirect form of communication. Vashti and Kuno have a much more transparent and open relationship than Captain Everard and the protagonist from In the Cage despite the indirectness of their relationship compared to Captain Everard and the protagonist’s relationship.
    
      As evident from the events in The Machine Stops and In the Cage, relationships and human connection takes work. It is far from reaching out to a new person and expecting to get along perfectly. It takes a mutual understanding from both parties and a willingness to make it work. As Zimmermann states, an emotional connection is challenging; it needs work, engagement, care about the Other, and nourishment. Developing friendship or a marriage for instance living the encounter with all the complexity and expressivity that it requires (43).
    
      By itself, communication technology doesn’t have the inherent ability to affect the relationships between humans. However, communication technology gives us the opportunity for more human interaction. It is up to humans to utilize that resource for what it is. This fact is displayed both in The Machine Stops and In the Cage. In In the Cage, the direct face-to-face communication between Captain Everard and the protagonist doesn’t make their relationship any better. The protagonist is still oblivious to the actual reason for Captain Everard's interactions. 
    
      In contrast, in The Machine Stops, Vashti and Kuno don’t directly communicate for much of their lives. However, despite mainly communicating through the Machine, they truly understand one another and have a genuine mother-son relationship even as their world collapses around them. In the end, communication technology is a tool for humankind. And like all tools, it is up to the wielder to correctly utilize it.
    
      --------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------
    
      Sanjana Nandi is a Cornell University student and a communication technology researcher.
    
    To view or add a comment, sign in
Stay updated on your professional world
  By clicking Continue to join or sign in, you agree to LinkedIn’s User Agreement, Privacy Policy, and Cookie Policy.

    New to LinkedIn? Join now
</code></pre></div></div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Due to the COVID-19 pandemic, everything from business meetings to college classes has moved to a digital format. With the rapid increase in the use of Zoom and other forms of digital communication, the effect of communication technology on human relationships has been questioned.]]></summary></entry></feed>